Guide to the Merrill Opera Video Collection ARS.0034
Archive of Recorded Sound
Merrill Opera Video Collection
1946-1994
ARS.0034
6 boxes: 221 videocassettes (199 VHS; 22 Betamax)
Archive of Recorded Sound
Unpublished opera productions on videocassette, from the collection of Greg Merrill Fe de Montreve.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The Merill Opera Video Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by by the estate of Greg Merrill Fe de Montreve in 2004.
Scope and Contents
Unpublished opera productions on videocassette, from the collection of aficionado Greg Merrill Fe de Montreve. Featuring both live performances and filmed versions, the operas generally fall within the established canon; there are multiple works by Massenet, Offenbach, Verdi, Donizetti, Mozart, and Wagner. Several are from the Metropolitan Opera, but there are productions from around the world, with many familiar names in starring roles. In general, personnel and location are listed on cassettes. Some performances are in English translation. Few productions are dated precisely, although the majority are from the 1970s and 80s. Given the printed labels, most tapes were probably bought or traded from dealers, especially those assigned numbers. The Betamax cassettes all have handwritten labels, which suggest home recording. Titles are transcribed as on the labels.
Operas
- 1. Numbered VHS tapes
  - 1. Yellow label (Box 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Vagabond King; Monte Carlo; Love Me Tonight; Jeanette on TV
  - 2. ODV prefix (Box 5)
    - 1229. Rossini - Semiramade, 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1486. McCormack documentary, 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1861. Handel - Rodelinda, 1973 (Box 5)
    - 1864. Donizetti - Lucia di Lammermoor, 1982 (Box 5)
    - 1989. Life of Alfredo Kraus, 1994 (Box 5)
  - 3. Sony brand
    - 1241. Il Trovatore (Box 5)
    - 1612. Il Grillo Del Focolare (Box 5)
    - 1629. Orlando Furioso (Box 5)
    - 1630. Agnese Di Hohenstaufen (Box 5)
    - 1631. L'Italiana in Algeri pt.1 (Box 5)
  - 4. Black and white printed labels
    - 1344. Donizetti - Anna Bolena (Box 5)
    - 1528. Donizetti - Lucrezia Borgia (Box 5)
    - 1637. Flotow - Martha (Box 5)
    - 1802. Donizetti - Lucia di Lammermoor (Box 5)
    - 1820. Verdi - Nabucco (Box 5)
    - 1882. Donizetti - Lucrezia Borgia (Box 5)
    - 1955. Verdi - Nabucco (Box 5)
    - 8055. Gigli Collection (Box 5)
    - 8119. Verdi - Nabucco (Box 5)
    - 8309. Verdi, Gigli (Box 5)
    - 8335. 2 Gigli Documentaries 1984, 1990 (Box 5)
    - 8340. Bellini - I Puritani (Box 5)
    - 8441. Offenbach - Les Contes (Box 5)
    - 8455. Carlo Bergonzi Recital, 1987 (Box 5)
    - 8465. Centenary of the Gramophone, 1989 (Box 5)
    - 8576. Trois Hommes En Habit (Box 6)
    - 8682. Verdi - Nabucco (Box 6)
    - 8713. Verdi - Nabucco (Box 6)
    - 8776. Bergonzi Recital (Box 6)
    - 8803. Handel - Alcina (Box 6)
    - 8879. Verdi - Nabucco (Box 6)
    - 8894. Auber - Fra Diavolo (Box 6)
    - 8908. Mozart - Die Zauberflote (Box 6)
    - 8910. Puccini - Madame Butterfly (Box 6)
    - 8917. Verdi - Rigoletto (Box 6)
    - 8923. La Scala Re-Building 50th Anniversary (Box 6)
- 2. Unnumbered VHS tapes (printed labels)
  - Auber - Fra Diavolo, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Bellini - Norma 1/18/1977, 5/7/1981 (Box 1)
  - Bellini - I Puritani, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Bellini - La Somnabula (Box 1)
  - Berlioz - Benvenuto Cellini 9/25/1982, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Bizet - Carmen 1980, 8/1/1981 (Box 1)
  - Boito - Mefistofele, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Borodin - Prince Igor, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Cavalli - L'Egisto, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Chabrier - L'Etoile, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Cherubin - Demophoon, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Cherubin - Medea, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Cimarosa - Den Gifte Stackar'n (Box 1)
  - Cimarosa - Il Fanatico Burlato (Box 1)
  - Cimarosa - Il Matrimonio Segreto, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Debussy - Pelleas et Melisande, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - Anna Bolena, 1984-06 (Box 2)
  - Donizetti - Don Pasquale, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - L'Eliser d'Amore, 1983-07-10 (Box 2)
  - Donizetti - La Favorita, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - La Fille Du Regiment, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - Lucia Di Lammermoor, 1982-08-21 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - Lucrezia Borgia 2/29/1980, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Donizetti - Maria Di Rohan, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - Maria Di Rudenz, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - Roberto Devereux, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Donizetti - Sancia Di Castiglia, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Gounod - Faust 9/9/1973, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Gounod - Mireille, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Gounod - Romeo and Juliet, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Handel - Giulio Casare, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Haydn - Lo Speziale, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Humperdinck - Hansel und Gretel, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Janacek - Cunning Little Vixen, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Janacek - Jenufa, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Janacek - Katya Kabanova (Box 2)
  - Joplin - Treemonisha, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Kalman - Czardasfurstin, 1984-01-02 (Box 2)
  - Lehar - Die Lustige Witwe, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Leoncavallo - Pagliacci, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Lortzing - Zar und Zimmermann, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Mascagni - Cavalleria Rusticana, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Mascagni - Iris, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Massenet - Cendrillon, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Massenet - Don Quichotte, 1980-06-29 (Box 2)
  - Massenet - Herodiade, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Massenet - Manon, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Massenet - Thais, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Massenet - Werther 1979, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Meyerbeer - Robert Le Diable (Box 2)
  - Milhaud - Cristofe Coulombe (Box 2)
  - Mozart - Cosi Fan Tutte, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Mozart - Don Giovanni, 1977-01-16 (Box 3)
  - Mozart - Die Entfuhrung Aus dem Serail, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Mozart - Idomeneo, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Mozart - Le Nozze di Figaro, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Mussorgsky - Boris Godunov, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Mussorgsky - Khovanschina 1979, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Offenbach - La Belle Helene, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Offenbach - Les Contes D'Hoffmann, 1981-01-02 (Box 3)
  - Offenbach - La Grande Duchesse de Gerolstein, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Offenbach - La Perichole, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Offenbach - Robinson Crusoe, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Ponchielli - La Gioconda, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Poulenc - Dialogues of the Carmelites, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Puccini - La Boheme, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Puccini - La Rondine (Box 3)
  - Puccini - Tosca, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Puccini - Turandot 6/1981, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Rimsky-Korsakov - Sadko, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Rossini - Barber of Seville, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Rossini - La Gazza Ladra, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Rossini - Semiramide (Box 3)
  - Saint-Saens - Samson et Dalila, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Shostakovich - Lady Macbeth of Minsk, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Smetana - The Bartered Bride, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Strauss - Ariadne Auf Naxos, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Tchaikovsky - Eugene Onegin, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Tchaikovsky - Iolanthe (Box 4)
  - Tchaikovsky - Pique Dame (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Aida, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Un Ballo in Maschera, 1978-01-12 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Don Carlo, 1978-01-08 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Macbeth, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Otello, 1976-12-07 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Rigoletto, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - Simon Boccanegra, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Verdi - La Traviata 1971, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Der Fliegende Hollander, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Die Meistersinger (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Das Ring Des Nibelungen. Gotterdamerung (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Das Ring Des Nibelungen. Das Rheingold (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Das Ring Des Nibelungen. Siegfried (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Das Ring Des Nibelungen. Die Walkure (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Parsifal, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Wagner - Tristan und Isolde 1985, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Weber - Der Freischutz, 1983-07-24 (Box 5)
  - Zandonai - Francesca da Rimini, 1980 (Box 5)
- 3. Sutherland, Pavarotti tapes (Box 6)
  An Evening With Joan Sutherland and Luciano Pavarotti; Joan Sutherland and Luciano Pavarotti Concert in Sydney; Joan Sutherland, La Stupenda BBC 1991
- 4. Beta tapes (handwritten labels) (Box 6)
  Song O' My Heart, Concert Sequence; CA Zephyr; Verdi - Falstaff BBC 72; Ernani, Met 12/17/83; Ludwig Brahms Concert/Old Met Shorts; Fortz - Caballe; La Giaconda; Broslovsky, Berlin Philharmonic; Trains/Great Caruso; Gayarre; Moonlight Sonata/Paderewski; I Sing For You Alone, Tito Schipa; Don Carlo, Met Pt.2 1983; Centennial Met Gala 1983; Fidelio 1/78; Don Pasquale